I decided to make this
acknowledgement or
announcement because we
are in a time of transition
between the most
comprehensive American Heart
Association, American
College of Cardiology,
2017 guidelines for
hypertension, and the
newly released 2025
guidelines for hypertension.
We are still trying
to shy away from the
2017 and trying to
increasingly adapt
the 2025 guidelines, but
there is some debate and
ongoing discussion regarding
the new guidelines.
Up till now, we have the
most recent version of
Harrison Principle of
Internal Medicine, and it
doesn't mention anything
about these new guidelines.
Maybe in the next
edition, we will have
more to learn about these
new adapted guidelines.
Please note guidelines
are recommendations
based on systematic reviews
of clinical evidence,
but physicians may
still use their clinical
judgment when they
manage their patients.
So you can use still your
clinical judgment as a
physician knowing your patients
and their demographics.
While the blood pressure
classification stays
the same for both
guidelines, 2017 and 2025,
there are some differences
when it comes to both.
So the first difference is
regarding the risk assessment
tool and the risk score.
So when it comes to 2017
guidelines, they use
something called pooled cohort
equation or MED calc or
acylosclerosis cardiovascular
disease risk calculator.
and a score of 10 or
greater was considered to
be a high-risk score that
qualified patient to have
antihypertensive medications.
When it comes to the
new guidelines, 2025,
they use a different
risk assessment
tool called the
Prevent Risk Calculator
and their high risk
is 7.5 or greater.
So they were very
or more strict
when compared to
the 2017 guidelines.
Both calculators
are based on patient
history and demographics
and also some blood
parameters like lipid
profile, diabetes,
systolic blood pressure,
etc.
You plug in these parameters
in both calculators and
you get a risk score. And
based on the risk score,
you decide if your patient
risk is high or not and
if they are candidate for
antihypertensive therapy.
For the purpose of our
lecture, we're going to use
risk of 7.5 or greater
to be a high risk, which
qualify your patient for
blood pressure medication.
So keep that in mind
because on slide 8, which
will talk about the goals,
you may be a little bit
confused because that
goes to the old guideline.
So I want to you, for
the sake of this lecture,
slide 8, the goal,
the high risk is
considered 7.5 or
greater. 7.5 or greater.
When it comes to the goal for
treatment, the goal
for treatment too,
so any patient, any
patient, including healthy
adults, should have a goal
of less than one theory,
less than 80 millimeter
mercury. So the new guidelines
are more strict when it
comes to blood pressure
control. The old guidelines,
2017 guidelines, were
a little bit more flexible
with older 60 years of
age or greater or young
healthy adult, and they
were only strict with
patients with chronic kidney
disease and diabetes
regardless of the age. The new
guidelines are strict with
everyone. They want the
blood pressure goal to be
less than 130, less than
80. And that also indicates
how to try to be more
rigorous to prevent more
cardiovascular disease,
heart attacks, strokes,
and more on the rise,
dementia, which is
very important. Despite
the differences between
both guidelines,
both aimed for early
treatment, which significantly
reduce cardiovascular
disease and dementia.
Okay,
you may still learn more about
the new 2025 hypertension
guideline during your
upcoming clerkship years
when they are more broadly
used. So to summarize,
my lecture is mainly discussing
the management of hypertension.
We're going to use a risk
score of 7.5 or greater
to qualify for
antihypertensive medication.
We are discussing two
domains of antihypertensive
treatment, lifestyle
modifications, which
are very important. and
you have to reassess
every step of the way
when you are treating this
patient with blood
pressure medication. And
we're going to also discuss
the pharmacotherapy.
Pharmacotherapy entails
principal antihypertensive
medication, which should be
used first, and then other
adjuvant medication, which can
help with the blood pressure
as they treat other comorbid
conditions, and we'll
give you examples. All will
be highlighted through a
clinical vineyard type of
scenario and you're going to
practice as if you are seeing
a patient in real life.
We're also going to
touch on the hypertensive
emergency and urgency and
we're going to also show
how is the difference when
it comes to treatment.
Other than that, everything
is straightforward. No
focus on numbers, no focus
on calculators. That's
what you want to learn.
If you have any question,
and you need to clarify
anything, please reach
out to me. I will be happy
to assist you. I can be
reached via email. My
email, immomorad at nyit
.edu. Please enjoy your lecture
and best of luck. Thank
you and have a wonderful
afternoon. Take care.